Anton Shirikov

Ph.D. Candidate, University of Wisconsin-Madison 110 North Hall, 1050 Bascom Mall, Madison, WI, 53706

☑ shirikov@wisc.edu ♀ shirikov.com │ Updated: Mar. 12, 2021

I am a political scientist working on media, propaganda, and the mechanisms of authoritarian rule. I also study legacies of authoritarianism and contemporary political institutions in post-communist countries. My research primarily relies on surveys and experimental methods.

EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin–Madison, Ph.D. Candidate in Political Science Expected Summer 2021

Dissertation: Who Trusts Untrustworthy Media? Partisanship and Information Credibility in Authoritarian Regimes

My dissertation project examines why authoritarian state-run media are popular and trusted, despite their strong pro-government bias. I use original experiments and surveys, conducted in Russia, as well as cross-national survey data to show that autocrats can rely on political biases to prop up their rule. Government loyalists find state-controlled media more trustworthy and more objective, and they rely on such media more in their news processing. My study demonstrates that the polarization of political beliefs can improve the stability of autocratic regimes. I also examine how exposure to state propaganda affects one's ability to critically evaluate news information.

University of Wisconsin–Madison, M.A. in Political Science 2016 Moscow State Institute of International Relations, Candidate of Sciences in Political Science 2007 European University at St. Petersburg, M.A. in Political Science 2005

WORKING PAPERS

"Who Trusts State-Run Media? Polarized Perceptions of Credibility in Non-Democracies"

"Fake News and the Polarization of Beliefs in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia"

"Is Trust in Media Decreasing? Evidence from the World Values Survey"

"A Model of Censorship and Propaganda" (with Scott Gehlbach, Zhaotian Luo, and Dmitriy Vorobyev)

"The Oligarch Vanishes: Defensive Ownership, Property Rights, and Political Connections" (with John Earle, Scott Gehlbach and Solomiya Shpak) *Under Review*

"Who Gets Ahead in Authoritarian Parliaments? The Case of Russian State Duma" Under Review

"Smart Ways to Use a Postcommunist Dummy" (with Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera)

PUBLICATIONS

2020. "Eurasia and Post-Communism: Weasel Words?" East European Politics and Societies & Cultures, Vol.34, No.2. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Dmitrii Kofanov.

2018. "Sovereignty and Regionalism in Eurasia." In: Paasi, Anssi, John Harrison, and Martin Jones (eds.). *Elgar Handbook on the Geographies of Regions and Territories*. Edward Elgar Publishing. With Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera.

2013. "Public Administration in Russia." In: Liebert, Saltanat, Stephen E. Condrey, and Dmitry Goncharov (eds.). Public Administration in Post-Communist Countries: Former Soviet Union, Central and Eastern Europe, and Mongolia. Routledge. With Dmitry Goncharov.

2010. Anatomiya Bezdeistviya. Politicheskiye Instituty i Konflikty v Budgetnom Processe Regionov Rossii [The Anatomy of Inaction. Political Institutions and Conflicts in the Budget Process of Russia's Regions] (in Russian). Saint-Petersburg: EUSP Press.

CONFERENCES AND INVITED TALKS

2021: Populism and the Pandemic lecture series (UW–Madison); A Day of Experiments in Memory of Professor Rebecca Morton (NYU-CESS, a poster presentation); Wisconsin Russia Project Young Scholars Conference (UW–Madison)

2020: Kyiv School of Economics; ASEES Annual Convention; APSA Annual Meeting; Communication Crossroads conference (UW–Madison)

2019: Studying Russia and the Postcommunist World (Harriman Institute, Columbia University); ASEES Annual Convention (San Francisco); MPSA Annual Conference (Chicago)

2018: ASEES Annual Convention (Boston); Wisconsin Russia Project Young Scholars Conference (UW–Madison); Regime Evolution, Institutional Change, and Social Transformation in Russia: Lessons for Political Science (Yale University); MPSA Annual Conference (Chicago)

2017: ASEES Annual Convention (Chicago); The Annual Meeting of the Society for Political Methodology (UW–Madison); Workshop on Research Design for Causal Inference (Northwestern University)

OTHER PUBLIC TALKS

"Russia's Strategies in Foreign Elections: What Does the Kremlin Want?" (A workshop for Wisconsin educators)

GRANTS AND AWARDS

ASEES Summer Dissertation Writing Grant (\$6,000)

2020

Summer Initiative Award from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016

Graduate student research award from the Center for Russia, East Europe, and Central Asia at UW–Madison (\$4,000)

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$16,000; joint with Georgiy Syunyaev). Project title: "Learning about Bias: An Experiment on News Consumption in Russia" 2020

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$10,245). Project title: "Perceptions of Media Credibility in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia"

University Fellowship, UW-Madison

2015-2016

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Kathryn Hendley (UW–Madison)

Research Assistant for Nadav Shelef (UW–Madison)

Summer 2020

Research Assistant for Scott Gehlbach (UW–Madison)

2016-2018

TEACHING

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Instructor, Math Camp for incoming graduate students in political science 2020, 2019

Teaching assistant, PS170: Research Methods in Political Science (Prof. Jessica Weeks) 2020, 2018

Lab instructor, PS919: Intro to Machine Learning (Prof. Adeline Lo) 2020

Teaching assistant, PS120: Politics Around the World (Prof. Nils Ringe) 2019

SERVICE

Peer reviews of manuscripts for American Journal of Political Science, Post-Soviet Affairs, Problems of Post-Communism, East European Politics

Co-organizer of the **Comparative Politics Working Group** for graduate students (UW–Madison) 2019-present

Graduate student coordinator for the **Comparative Politics Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019 Graduate student coordinator for the **Political Economy Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association; Midwest Political Science Association; Association for Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies (ASEEES)

SOFTWARE

R, Python, Stata, LaTeX, RMarkdown, HTML, Shiny, Git, Qualtrics

OTHER EXPERIENCE

I have previously worked as deputy editor-in-chief and editor-in-chief at Slon.ru, as opinions editor at RBC, and as editor at McKinsey & Company (all in Moscow, Russia).

REFERENCES

Yoshiko M. Herrera, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, yherrera@wisc.edu

Scott Gehlbach, Department of Political Science and Harris School of Public Policy, University of Chicago, gehlbach@uchicago.edu

Rikhil R. Bhavnani, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, bhavnani@wisc.edu